Tyrone Rutherford

Coleford - Forest of Dean, 07718274127, tyrutherford@hotmail.co.uk, LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/tyrone-rutherford-abb10787/
Github: https://github.com/TR94

Frontend developer skills in HTML, CSS and JavaScript. Student with Code Institute on a Full Stack Software Development Diploma. Moving industries from Manufacturing to Software and looking for the first new role as a frontend developer.

Profile:

Front End Developer establishing experience in building responsive websites using HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. Currently studying **Full Stack Software Development course with Code Institute** after a career change from 10 years of Manufacturing Engineering. Focusing on developing clean, easy to follow and efficient code and comfortable working in a regulated and delivery orientated environment. Looking to secure an opportunity as a Junior Front End Developer that will allow me to build on my skills and lay the foundations for my career in the Software Industry.

Core Tech Skillset:

Front End	Back End	Source Control	UI / UX	Frameworks
HTML	Python	GitHub	Wireframes (Balsamiq)	Bootstrap
CSS				Working on JQuery
JavaScript				

Soft skills:

All the skills listed below are interlinked and are utilised at different times to get the best output:

- **Team work**: Having worked in larger project teams (around 15-20) and smaller departments of 2-3 I understand the role I play in being a reliable part of the working community and how to effectively collaborate to meet strict delivery targets.
- **Communication**: As part of working in a team effective communication with work colleagues and also clients is critical to progress projects efficiently. This is done formally through presenting data in a clear and concise way and informally through building working relationships.
- Leadership: Having lead projects and production teams, I have demonstrable experience of understanding team strengths and weaknesses whilst managing clear instruction, decision making, as well as knowing when to escalate for support.
- **Resilience**: Working life has taught me the perseverance to get the job done even when it becomes difficult or the scope changes. Being a reliable part of the team by not giving up until the job is complete.
- **Engaging**: Thriving in a fast paced environment with the ability to work under pressure to problem solve and find solutions quickly.
- **Process driven**: A working life from the Aerospace and Medical industry has cemented the ability to follow process and documentation. This includes scoping change requirements, managing revision control and being able to present change for approval.

Coding Projects:

Battleships - Portfolio project 3 of 5

Completed 16/07/2023

- A Python based game based on the classic "Battleships" game. This back end programme allows the
 player to customise the size of the board and number of ships for the game. The game plays using a
 randomised computer generated opponent and features game boards that track hits and misses
 throughout the rounds.
- This project was written from scratch with the focus on Python code. It is hosted using a Code Institute mock terminal that allows the back-end code to be used in a web browser.
- Link to the Github repository where the ReadMe can be found and a link to the live site.

Rock, Paper, Scissors, Lizard, Spock Game - Portfolio project 2 of 5

Completed 09/06/2023

- Based on the popular Big Bang Theory television series game, this website allows the user to play the game against a computerised component. Modelled off a random number generator, the code makes a selection and determines the outcome based on the player's selection.
- This project was written from scratch with the focus on JavaScript code. HTML and CSS is used to create the basic form of the page.
- Link to the Github repository where the ReadMe can be found and a link to the live site.

Kiwi Cocktail Bar - Portfolio project 1 of 5

Completed 29/04/2023

- A demonstration website created to brand and market a fictitious new cocktail bar. The site uses multiple pages showing off what the bar has to offer in a responsive and interactive way.
- This project was written from scratch and predominately focuses on HTML and CSS language
- Link to the Github repository where the ReadMe can be found and a link to the live site.

Tech Interests:

- Currently learning the Python language and will be developing a project to contribute towards the Full Stack Developer Diploma course.
- Monitoring AI progression, curious how this will affect not only the software industry but day to day life.
- Keen to learn more about Frameworks, such as JQuery and Django, specifically how they can be used as building blocks for unique coding projects.

Education:

- Code Institute: Full Stack Software Development Diploma, in progress completion due March 2024.
- Bournemouth University: Bachelors Engineering, First Class Honours. Foundation Degree Engineering in Manufacturing Management, Distinction.
- The College, Poole: HNC Mechanical Design, Distinction; Subsidiary Diploma fast track, Distinction; NVQ Engineering Technical Services Lv3, NVQ Performing Engineering Operations Lv2, BTec Lv2 Engineering.
- The Thomas Hardye School, A-Levels: Mathematics A, Further Mathematics B, Product Design A, Physics B.

Work Experience

Career break June 2023 - Present

• Studying Code Institute Full Stack Developer course (Feb 2023 - Feb 2024) and travelling in my camper van around the UK and Europe (will be back in the UK in September).

Freelance Online Review Writer @ Offroad.CC

February 2021 - Present

• Working for an online magazine writing reviews for mountain bike products. Includes researching, testing and critiquing the product alongside writing a balanced and engaging review.

Process Engineer at Creo Medical, Chepstow, NP16 5UH (Endoscopic surgical devices)

Jul 2022 - May 2023

- Led and mentored a newly implemented change control process within a team of 8 Process Engineers.
- Standardisation of assembly process and production line layout for an electrical energy generator which took production output from 2-3 per week to 20 per week and improved quality
- Production line layout and flow line implementation on endoscopic device product which improved quality yield from ~40% to ~85+% along with faster manufacturing times.

Project Engineer at AK Industries, Hereford, HR2 6JQ (Injection moulding)

August 2021 - June 2022

- Customer interaction from project inception up to the production phase
- Management of engineering change control and new product introduction into an injection moulding manufacturing factory.
- Management of non-released production trials through the factory
- Reporting to the customer of progress of tool manufacture, trial outcomes and timelines

Production Engineer at ABT Products, Ross-on-Wye, HR9 7BW (Sheet metal fabrication and welding)

October 2020 – July 2021

- Responsibilities include solving manufacturing and quality issues for sheet metal welded fabrications and assemblies.
- Driving continuous improvement on current processes to save cost and increase productivity.
- Experience using CAD to developing jigs / fixtures and update drawings based on continuous improvement activities.
- Owning the end to end solution from problem identification, idea generation, design, manufacture, implementation and feedback.

Value Stream Lead at Cobham Mission Systems, Wimborne, BH21 2BJ Oct 2018 – Oct 2020 (Air to air refuelling equipment)

- Accountable for product delivery for 2 production cells (Probes and Rails) with a combined revenue target of £15M (2020).
- Successful delivery involved working with a wide range of stakeholders across the business. Monitoring the supply chain and working with procurement to prioritise delivery of key components.
- A dedicated material planner, manufacturing engineer and 4 shop floor fitters took direction from me on a day to day basis, managing and prioritising their workload. In the wider business I collaborated with goods in, dispatch, inspection, supplier quality, design engineering and quality to solve problems quickly.
- Experience with handling customers and suppliers as required and exposure to company audits.

Graduate at Cobham plc, Wimborne, BH21 2BJ

Sept 2016 - Sept 2018

6 months placements included:

- ERoW Programme Management, KC-390 WARP & Probe Assisting the project manager with reporting, scheduling and budget reviews as well as managing the delivery of Ground Support Equipment to the customer.
- ERP Implementation Analyst

 Supporting the implementation of a new ERP system into a £140M aircraft operation business.

 Learning business processes and understanding how the new system will affect people's day to day inhs
- Chief Operations Office Analyst
 Exposure to high level management of functional leads and to the wider thinking and planning of future business trajectory.
- Global Operations and Manufacturing Strategy Analyst
 Reviewing the manufacturing strategy of a £4bn company. Gathering and analysing data to make
 decisions on future investments and divestments with the aim to increase productivity and profit
 margin.

Apprentice at Cobham plc, Wimborne, BH21 2BJ

Sept 2012 - Sept 2016

- 4 month placement in Product Quality
- 2 month placement in Manufacturing Engineering
- 3 month placement in Engineering, Development and Test
- 1.5 year placement as a Business Analyst on the Organisational Design Programme
- 1.25 year placement in Strategic Sourcing, Group Spend Analyst Project Lead
- Aerospace & Defence Procurement Group, Next Generation (July '15 Sep '16)
- Member of the Cobham STEM Council (Nov 2015 Jun 2017)